holotalk and profiles in holography is
brought to you through the generous
support of the international holography
fund for more information visit their
website at holographyfund.org
[Laughter]
[Music]
hello hello is this Martin Richardson hi
speaking how are you this is Frank de
Freitas hiya Frank uh of course you know
this is the hollow talk show
which I'm not sure if you're aware of it
or not but I bring holographers on and
interview them and have been doing that
for a number of years I've been
following your work for some time now
Frank well thank you you do a great show
well thank you very much it's not my
first calling in life but I decided to
do it and uh
anyway it's good to have you on and I
know everyone's going to love hearing
about you but there's so many things to
cover with Martin Richardson that I
don't even know where to start but I
guess maybe we could start with you
little bit of your early history on how
you got started with holography and then
we can move on to some of your projects
and your books and your presentations in
the conferences that you've been
involved with and
take it from there but what about your
early work how did you get started with
holography in the first place
um
I am in London was the first Contact I
had with
um with the Dennis Gabor hologram okay
the uh amazing meter Square hologram
that I think was created by Nick
Phillips I'm not sure that was the laser
transmission hologram of him behind the
desk is that correct yes
um so that was my initial you know
content with me as a kid
and I guess it it sort of stuck with me
from there it wasn't until I went to art
school and in the early sort of 70s mid
70s I met a guy called Paul Wharton
who was working with
Rebecca I think it's Rebecca Rebecca
Booth or Roberta Booth okay yes
um
goldsmiths University and that was about
1980. I believe it's Roberta Booth
Roberta Roberta booth and Rebecca deem
Arthur
two great ladies of philography yes
um and I when I was an evening course
with Paul Walton and made my first tiny
hologram
hologram which was uh very difficult to
see it was like looking into a muddy
puddle and uh it was piece of magic for
me
and uh you know I began to read more
about the way holography was being
developed by people like um my opinion
and uh bill mortini in the states
and the more I heard about these things
the more my interests grew
and uh really it's been a a lifelong
experience ever since now
I had a chance to see a few of your
pieces on the web in the Jonathan Ross
collection right
stand you have a website of your own
which is updated regularly so I'll
include a link to that
but I believe I may have a chance to see
one of your Works personally you may
have been in an exhibit in the museum
photography it was called holography
redefined or something like that yeah
yeah
now you did you specialize in
portraiture work because I noticed a
number of portraits that were in
different collections
um it wasn't until I basically kissed my
Master's Degree at the Royal College of
Art that I began to specialize in in
portraiture was that a hallography
degree that you obtained there the
Masters but when I began at the Royal
College of 19
and there was already had sand table
established by somebody you may have
heard of that so just lies oh absolutely
an amazing chemist he's working in
Cambridge University at the moment
and in fact I'm going to be working on a
project in the near future with Jeff
recording the Harrison clocks from the
Greenwich observatory in London
on a project to do with longitude
um but when I enrolled at the Royal
College we were working in the sand
table and completed my masters in
holography there in 1984 and then the
pepper was my external supervisor for
that
so another name there andy pepper oh yes
absolutely uh but the Royal College
didn't get their first place
I graduated and then I came back the
following year and completed the PHD
which uh gave me the opportunity to
start working with pulse lasers and met
people like a
Greener or who'd open up the Richmond
holographic Studios wow what great work
came out of there incredible stuff it
was so groundbreaking
you know I remember seeing the first
part of holograms today
John Webster of Boy George
yes I remember that
I mean I mean these were 50 by 60
60 acromat reflection piece
mind-blowing
so lots of ground was being broken there
and I suppose at the same time people
like um Eve richer was developing
exhibition
light dimensions and uh that really sort
of brought my work to the you know sort
of public awareness yeah and uh it was
it was a good time for a little
did I noticed one of one of your pieces
was a pulse reduction did that come out
of RCA as well yes it did yeah yeah
that's interesting see I have one from
Jonathan cope
and uh you don't see very many of them
Fred untocr had actually did the only
one and I saw many years ago that was on
display here in the U.S
right yeah
you get involved with so many of the
Stars
any celebrity type of holographic
portraiture how does someone even get
into that realm do you go over to David
Bowie's house and have breakfast or
something or what yeah you do
fantastic he collects Holograms no
kidding
um one of the first he collected was by
um
Peter and Anna Marie Nicholson oh no
oh no I think they sh they shot it um a
post-hologram of one of the stage sets
he was involved in designing for the
glass spider tour
and this was a 50 by 60 piece and uh
that was one of his first ever
wow so he's very supportive of the field
of holography huh he speaks very highly
of that Davis is one of these um in a
very intelligent people that like to
keep a finger on anything that's new and
you need
technology
plus is that evident from his website
um
just met him when I visited an
exhibition he was having in London and
it was one of those occasions where
um you know he's a sort of a demigod and
nobody really wanted to embarrass Ed To
Us by talking to him and I took a deep
breath walked out to him and started to
talk about holography and he said to me
well would you like to design an album
cover and that's something I did for
his ala's album which was which was
written in 1999
and went to New York we've struck up a
friend
a friend
I made a small film of him shot with the
stereo round system from what was then
applied holographic it was a camera
designed by
um Craig newswanger
and uh
that footage as soon uh
it's been copied into a reflection uh
digital hologram by giola oh my baby
60 years old isn't it something
incredible yeah here we go
enjoy it while we got it man because
time is ticking down you know what I
mean
well I'm not I'm not real familiar with
David
that much
it's known throughout the world and it's
very nice that he's been supportive with
holography and found it fascinating
enough to
to I don't know where he would be if
you're with it
like a once and done type of
crush or something or is it an ongoing
interest that he still has to this day
um no I didn't think it is I think um
the door's still open there there's as
as we know there's lots of new things
happening with
diagrammatic emulsions and full color
and you know the amazing work that Mike
Luke and Craig newsbanger are working on
at zebra at the moment which is is
really um
or inspiring and it's the type of thing
that I'm sure Bowie would be receptive
to
um it's it's just you know it's a
progression of time and and getting the
right Energies
is the right window of opportunity to to
show to somebody like David Bowie or one
of the other celebrities I've been you
know fortunate enough to work with and
just uh
if the timing's right then then they can
see an opportunity then certainly
they'll they'll use it to you know
promote holography to to where it should
be
through this media
now you have a book
a book Prime illusion what's the other
book besides Prime illusion the the
first book was called spacebomb space
bomb
uh you know I I play with words and uh
yes uh like to be as creative with uh
you know the stuff I put out as possible
and I I thought of a hologram as being a
sort of a you know a capture of space
and if the image is dynamic enough it's
a sort of a bomb so space bomb oh
absolutely
um and it it really documents my first
20 years involvement with
me from the early sculpture right
through
route uh the more you know Advanced uh
holographic pulse portraiture so space
Bond was the first and the second was
the Prime illusion which was the more I
suppose I suppose more I get more of an
academic attempt to ask the bigger
questions such as you know where are we
going with holography what does it mean
um
where does it philosophically
within Society now as Society is being
transformed by
um the answer of digital media how do
you feel about that about the digital
Technologies moving
taking some of the crafts
per ship away from the field yeah
definitely yeah
um I'm I'm I'm really excited by the uh
digital technology and holography I
think it's going to open up new Pathways
it's going to broaden the the entrance
point for young people coming in field
and um
you know a lot of has gone through this
sort of evolution and we we can spot the
evolution if we look at the early
reflection Al grounds from Dennis York
right through to
you know the stuff that I've already
mentioned my includes producing now and
um
you know it's only a time before it
starts it's somewhere
infiltrate into everyday life in a way
we couldn't possibly
uh imagine 20 years ago so digital
monography is you know certainly
exciting
do you feel that the digital aspect of
this is
probably going to give it the biggest
boost that anything in the past has
managed to do also the folk color as
well
um I think it's inevitable Frank
um if we if we consider a moment you
know one of the major factors of the
successful holographic image is
measurements being precise about the way
we do things from you know light meter
readings through to calibration of
materials and so on and so forth
the one big advantage to the digital
media now offers us is that we can be
more precise and more accurate Beyond
are done using analog technology before
Okay so
um
and also you see what what happens is it
opens up new possibilities in
the application of holographic
technology to the broader area of for
example architecture
certainly has to be seen in security and
and you know development
s there at the moment engineering as
well engineering so there will be this
sort of
um resurrection of Photography okay you
know about Steve Benson said it but
basically finding a new solution to to
hold problems but then maybe in a good
science is about that
do you think it will cut the value of
the r the Arctic work that has been
far by hand
do you think that will be just as much
appreciated in the future because
obviously working by hand we cannot
produce what can be done digitally right
and
well that sort of make handmade
holography go the way of handmade
cabinets
ah I don't know I'm not sure either I
don't I mean things like the the
projects that you and I are involved in
with the students you know Hands-On
photography
you really can't beat
sort of understanding Optics and what
light is from the experience of having
hands on one-to-one tuition of things
and recording a very small scale Dennis
your hologram of coins you know with a
diet laser with with a bunch of students
is always going to be a magical
experience yes in a given get that the
first time in their lives are truly
asking you know substantial questions
about
photonics and you know how a lens works
and what is what is uh what is light
what is light yes what what's like
what's the what's going on with the
chemical chart I mean I have students
coming into my lab who just can't
believe
how much they've learned at the end of
the day from making a very simple Dennis
shoe program yeah so for me I suppose
you know
um it's not an irrelevant question
because they're all there'll always be
the sort of appreciation for the the
handmade Holograms that we've seen from
people from you know Peter Miller
through to Mike barrage and Nick
Phillips early programs with the
Holocaust out and there's always
going to be a collectors
active Niche for that and I think it is
relevant that um times have changed
yes
I know I I fear that I may be reaching
the end
of my involvement with the progress of
holography because I I sort of draw the
line at
Automation and thing I I I I I like
holography the same way that you go to
someone who builds cabinets or builds
handmade tables or chairs
I don't know
you know the piece you get when you when
you're in lab alone and you're just
staring at the the spread Beam on the
wall and you know the the
environment the the whole sort of piece
that you get from from being in that
situation peace is a very good word
and I got CEO you don't have that you
can't you don't afford to
afford that with digital holography
which tends to be an automated process
yes
so the
Montford University am I pronouncing
that correctly monster
diversity
this name has been involved with
holography for many many years hasn't it
yes this institution
um well originally it was formed the
Department of modern Optics was formed
by Professor Nick Phillips which would
have been I guess in the early 80s and
uh Nick as you know was responsible for
much of the import
processing regimes from Langford through
to Wilford and more recently with DuPont
and it's always been relatively high
profile and it's in its science space
and fairly recently Nick's team moved to
a new lab in Wales called optic technium
and yes yeah Nick was fortunate to team
up with and Bella Argan
who's again a pioneer of color Holograms
I'm sure you know house yes and
and I I happen to be around at the time
I'd been working
um in the holographic image studio in
central London for 20 years and I've I'd
reached the point where I felt that you
know most of my commercial
energies have been
um coming up sort of you know
my late 40s and it was time for me to
perhaps have a more serious stab at some
of the more but I felt the more
important issues
um questions I was asking about
holography
and I was offered
off at your mom for that senior research
fellow which um I jumped at I
immediately fell in love with the idea
of spending all my time teaching and
developing uh IP
successful in being awarded a chair at
De Montfort um just last year
congratulations thank you so I'm now the
professor of modern holography at De
Montfort University that's a great title
yeah I'm not quite sure what it means
maybe that's the idea and we're honored
to have you on the program thank you sir
oh it's an honor to uh to be interviewed
by you is this the same location now I'm
just going by memo
is this the same location where the uh
upcoming conference in September
holography in the modern museum is going
to be held yes yes okay so that's the
connection there that I that I caught on
okay yeah yeah what's the obsession with
three-dimensional Imaging anyway why do
we absolutely have to have a medium
that's three-dimensional isn't what we
have with our high resolution high
definition
enough you can trace it back through the
history of our price through to you know
the invention of perspective
um in the Italian Renaissance
um it's something to do with the
representation of reality and
um my my theory my take on this this
whole thing at the moment is
um
Today We Live we live such a fast-paced
you know fast-moving world that we
actually find security in things we know
are fakes
huh
say the word fakes f-a-k-e-s yeah huh
if we can identify something like a
hologram as being a representation of
the real world
okay and we know that to be a fake we
find we find a certain amount of
reassurance in that because if we know
if we know what a fake is we can then
begin to Define what reality isn't
it so I think that
that's my my take on why we're becoming
so obsessed currently you know with with
three-dimensional Imaging again
and of course everything is
three-dimensional today is called a
hologram which probably drives you nuts
as much as it drops it happened to me
this morning actually Frank somebody
sent me a link to that animated hologram
website and of course it turns out
the old Peppers goes to repackaged oh I
see yeah
and yeah what can we do about that I
don't know I wouldn't even go into some
of the emails that I get from the
general public all the time on stuff you
know yeah
the most bizarre stuff really yeah going
all the way to people who are saying
that there's neighbors projecting
three-dimensional Holograms into their
bedrooms at night and things yeah it's
like yeah I finally put on my email page
that if you see three-dimensional
at night in your bedroom floating around
the room please contact your doctor
not me
I want to be nasty to people but you
know that's that's another realm that
you're talking about it's not holography
that's that's a that's a
that's a that's a physician's problem
there with medication I'm sure
now you did a 3D conference and you have
a PowerPoint and an MP3 file at your
website that folks can
yeah is your book also available at
amazon.com
uh no but if if anyone is interested in
receiving a copy if they log on to my
website and send me an email with their
details I've got about
I've got about 100 100 copies I would be
able to send for three
for free you said yeah three
well
let me let me I was good I was gonna buy
one so let me get on that list
if it was at Amazon I was going to go
over and order it actually so let me get
on that list
and we'll see who else contacts you
we'll find out who really listens to
this show or not exactly exactly that's
going to be interesting isn't it
anything else you'd like to like that
coming up on 25 minutes and there's
really only so much and there's such a
varied audience that's listening to this
as well which is why I try and give a
little sample of uh of just about
everything that can be covered rather
than sticking on one specific
topic okay anything that you would like
the listeners to know about or to hear
about a table will be interesting Frank
is um
he mentions
with some of the you know famous people
I've worked with in the past and
the list is long as you know and you
know the list includes people like the
film director Martin school safety yeah
um
post Holograms with him to Painted Peter
Blake
the British father of what we referred
to as the pop pop art Alan Parker the
David Bowie images now all of these
Holograms all of these Masters are being
stored in some silver trunks in my lap
you know and I'm keeping them there for
posterity but the key question is what
happens to these are these when I'm no
longer around so what I'd like to hear
from your listeners is if anyone has a
suggestions what I can do with these
Holograms in the long term let me know
think of a deserving cause or a museum
that we could uh you know have these
Holograms donated to I would be
listening why isn't that something
well let's see what the listeners would
say I don't think you're going to hear
from any of the school students or
teachers but or many of the other people
who are listening but they may send
something to you but some of some of the
holographers out there may contact you
on that
have you contacted the international
holography fund or someone other I
consider that sort of a type of
governing organization
perhaps I'm very pleased to mentioned
that because I just I just wanted to say
how delighted I am that you know
something like this has come along and
it's a Lifeline to uh struggling artists
who really need help yeah and you know I
I much admired uh Posey Jackson's vote
with the sheer water and Andy Pappas
hard work in that and I can't tell you
how how much it's helped people in the
past and long mayor continue
future I agree I was actually
a recent of that for the whole talk
which I'm very proud to say fantastic
you know good cause there yes very much
and it is a tough field
no I mean you're talking about people
who have to sometimes
truly wonder where they're going to get
groceries
you know to put food on the table I'm
sure you have yeah I've seen it and
experienced it actually many times
it's very up and down like a roller
coaster it takes its toll on you after a
while too
yeah but here we are
still doing it you would think with all
the things that we're doing that uh
nothing would be a problem in our lives
you know
oh well hey it was our choice so you
know here's what we got so let's work we
wouldn't have it any other way I don't
think it could be any other way I look
back at a lifetime of this I don't know
what it could have been
well Martin I want to thank you very
much
I know everyone's going to enjoy
listening to your interview and it will
be archived over at the profiles and
holography website
I guess I should probably try and keep
these interviews a little bit more art
based considering it's uh you know art
and holography type of format for this
profiles and holography but it's also
good to get to know the artist a little
bit as well which I think we've
accomplished here today learning a
little about you thank you very much I
hope you get a chance to meet someday
I'm sure we will and I look forward to
the day when uh when all of you come
over here to the states and I
here because I I don't fly and that's
that's another one of my
drawbacks to actually accomplishing
anything in this field is not getting on
a plane
that is
you know when you have to drive
everywhere and it's like 18 hours to get
somewhere yeah yeah thank you so much
have a good rest of the day
thank you and uh
Kendon thank you for coming on the show
live long and prosper yes sir goodbye
cheers now